Hello, I'm Doctor Park Jong Chol.
Regrettably this is already the last lecture of fixture. As this is the last lecture,
I try to make it more informative and I hope you would enjoy this lecture. Let's begin.
Today I'm going to talk about implant surfaces. If you look at the advancement of implanted surfaces.
Implanted surfaces let me explain in the chronological order. Surface of implant the first generation surface was a simply cut machined surface.
The second generation surface was made rough to increase the surface area. At the third generation surface, the titanium's rough surface chemical properties were changed to accelerate the healing of implant.
In the future we'll have the fourth generation surface to have a better outcome with the biological properties. How and why the implant surfaces have been evolved definitely there are reasons for that so,
Today I'm going to look at how and for what purposes the implant surfaces have evolved?
First let's look at the first generation implant surface at the beginning the brain mark implant adapted.
The machined surface just the titanium was cut for the surface due to the property of titanium metal. It forms in a living body a stable oxide layer which delays illusion of titanium Ions improves biocompatibility is strongly corrosion resistant to blood works or liver.
Leading to osseointegration without a special treatment on the surface the roughness of machined the surface is determined by the cutting and the strength of titanium it differs from journal to journal but,
The average machine the surface roughness is about 0.5 to 0.8 micrometer. The smooth motion to surface success rate is about 80 percent under today's criteria the figure is very worrisome to enhance the success rate the second generation implant surface emerged.
The second generation implant surface has the characteristics is that it has better on the implant contact.
So The surface is made of rough. There are two ways to do so one is to attach rough particles on the surface of titanium and the other way is to roughen the surface by cutting. The first rough surface was made by straumann in the 1970s. It was tps surface with attached particles followed by rbm.
Which had rough surface by cutting now sla surface is mostly used. The first rough surface titanium plasma spray surface.
Tps surface is coated rapidly by spraying titanium particles at high temperature compared to the machined surface. The rough surface had the six times more surface area. It had superior stability and improved ocean integration. However at the too rough surface.
When it is exposed it was very challenging to clean the surface. So bone resorption accelerated also during tps fixture placement the titanium particles fell off to surrounding bone or tissue. So the outcome of the particle attached to the rough surface.
Fixture was not as good as expected. So a method of roughening the surface by spraying a medium of specific particles on the implant surface rpm emerged.
What you're seeing is the blasting on the surface of implant in this video. A certain medium is sprayed on the surface of implant after the blasting the smooth surface is turned into rough.
Turned into rough but there is a variation from paper to paper compared to the motion to surface it has the effect of increasing the surface area tremendously.
But ibm did not meet the expectations where the bone quality is not very good. So they developed sla surface with a rougher surface and the roughness the cells would like. After the blasting process acid etching process is added.
So through the two stages the surface is roughened. Currently to roughen the surface most companies adopt this sla approach but the quality varies from company to company. To make the sla surface first the blasting is used to create craters.
And the acid etching process creates micro pits. Through the two stages implant surface roughness is much higher than rbm. Increase of the roughness brought 45 percent increase in the surface area.
And bone to implant contact area such increase in the surface area is increasing the bone to implant contact leading to more solid ocean integration. If you look at the clinical case at 15 and 25 locations rbm fixtures were placed with the sinus lift but also integration was not achieved.
Therefore, they were replaced by sla implants and it became successful. As you can see in the case of the sla surface with more surface area brings better osseointegration and removal torque is much higher than rpm. Therefore sla approach is adapted by most companies to make the surface rough.
Next the third generation surface. It is characterized by making chemical properties of the implanted surface changed the first method is to use HA hydroxyapatite which has the same composition as bone to facilitate osseointegration plasma spray coating is used or a nano HA coating.
Or nano calcium phosphate coating is used the second method hydrophobic implant surface is turned into hydrophilic properties so that blood can adhere to it.
Regarding those two let me explain. First method HA coating. As you can see in the picture HA powder is sprayed on the titanium surface to do the coating it was started around 1984.
The initial bone reaction was pretty good. So many companies adapted that method. However five years post up the coded layer dissolved in the body. So they fell off such implants became mobile and fell off.
Therefore, they no longer made the implants anymore. If you look at here I placed a HA cordial implant at number 36 in 2011 seven years later in 2018. The patient came back complaining the mobility of the implant.
There was no gingiva inflammation or no bone resorption on x-ray.
When a check code is attached to usually no sign of inflammation or bone loss. Superstructure is removed fixture driver is connected with a force of about 10 newton centimeters. The fixture was turning super hydrophilic implant was placed which will be discussed later.
There's hardly any bone loss and the fixture was cleanly removed as the coated layer was absorbed the fixture was removed very cleanly. The second way of using a chain more uniform.
Holder layer can be made to increase the adhesive strength of the coated layer. If you compare these two coated layers left layer shows much more uniform layer which increases the adhesive strength.
Therefore fixtures do not need to be removed as you saw in the clinical case before. The second way to change the chemical properties of the surface is to provide super hydrophilicity to the rough surface to enable the blood wetting property.
Fast blood clot formation enables early osseointegration locally on the market are ostem CA BA straumann sl active products. Compared to the conventional service blood vettability is much better.
In order to acquire super hydrophilicity. First sla surface fixture is soaked in calcium solution to treat it with calcium ion. Then hydrophobic fixture would turn into hydrophilic fixture attracting more blood calcium iron treating.
Surface has better protein absorption than the conventional surface. The higher the protein absorption rate the better signaling to bring cells to the site facilitating healing. Fluorescent staining shows much higher protein absorption rate than the conventional surface.
The third characteristics of the calcium ion treated surfaces more blood clot formation in larger area. As was explained in the previous lecture of implant healing. Letter blood clot formation leads to better formation of fibrin network resulting in more stable and faster healing.
Compared to the conventional surface. There is a big difference in the blood clot formation. We can expect faster and more stable healing than the conventional surface.
The second way to increase hydrophilicity is the ostense BA surface. The SA surface is ultra thin need coated with the bio absorbency HA and hydrophilicity surface technology is applied to increase early.
Osseointegration performance 30 percent improvement over the sla surface. The degree of hydrophilicity determines the wettability of the fixture surface. The highest weatability is seen on the rightmost fixture.
Which looks wet with moisture. The picture with increased hydrophilicity has very high blood adhesion property.
This combines the advantages of sla surface and HA bone response to improve healing and shorten the implant healing process.
As soon before HA surface has the advantage of a good bone response accelerating early healing, but the problem is the coated layer is absorbed and detached by using ultrathin HA. The detaching issue is addressed and the ultra thin coat of HA is absorbed by the bone remodeling process.
Ultimately the ultra thin HA code facilitates osseointegration and is absorbed during the bone remodeling process. Overcoming the disadvantage of HA surface and sustained stable osseointegration for a long time.
At the end of the day the reason why we come up with this surface is that as discussed in the previous lecture.
The secondary stability process is facilitated and made more stable by increasing bone to implant contact more stable. Osseointegration can be facilitated as the surface treatment technology is evolving.
Recently other specific material is used for the coding to develop super hydrophilic surface technology. The blood vertebility is accelerated going one step further protein attachment ability is further increased. It will affect the cell formation which affect the healing more than 90 percent improvement in terms of protein adhesion compared to SA.
So this way the surface attribute technology is evolving quite rapidly blood clots can be more stably maintained in a wider area contributing to the osseointegration depending on the treatment done on the surface.
There is a big difference in terms of the blood clot formation compared to the conventional surface. The advanced surface makes much more blood clots over time.
You can see the difference of blood clot formation between these two in the containers. The blood clot formation facilitates the bone formation shorten the implant treatment time.
As discussed in the previous lecture. The implant healing curves the secondary stability curve will become steeper accelerating the healing time.
Let's summarize the third generation surface treatment. Fixture surface chemical properties are changed in terms of changing the hydrophobic property to hydrophilic property. Then why do we need a hydrophilic surface?
This is related to the previous lecture implant healing process. Osseointegration is based on the formation of the blood clots and the new bone formation cells come into the site. Newborn is formed between the implant and bone and they get integrated together. At this time if the influence surf is highly hydrophilic blood easily attached to the surface.
And the protein will attach more. The signals to call cells in there will improve and the energy on the implant surface rises making the environment favorable to the cells. Ultimately the time for secondary stability the osseointegration time will be shortened to reduce the time for implant treatment.
To achieve these objectives many companies made a lot of efforts and I've explained such efforts and how development has been made toward that end.
Now one step further, let's talk about the future surface technology. The fourth generation surface no such a products on the market yet but a lot of studies are going on regarding the biological properties.
For example growth factors can be collected from a patient's blood to facilitate the integration between an implant and bone. If you cannot understand it quite right prf or prp that is frequently seen in the clinical setting can be the examples.
This concludes the discussion on the fixture surface. Let's briefly summarize what we have talked about today. Implant fixture surface can be divided into four generations.
The first generation wishing to surface. The second generation the rough surface to increase the surface area. The third generation surface is changing the chemical property of the surface to facilitate the osseointegration.
The fourth generation is working on the bio property of the surface for the future the development of the fixture surface aims to shorten the osseointegration secondary stability period to accomplish the stable healing that is the purpose and meaning of the changes.
Through three lectures we talked about the fixtures. What do you think fixture design and surface changes have contributed to stability
And implant healing through the lectures. If you learn to choose appropriate implant fixtures for your patients, successful implanted treatment has already begun.
I hope you will have great opportunities. Thank you for staying with me until the last moment. Thank you.